<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England's advocate, Europe's monitor being an intreaty for help in behalf of the English silk-weavers and silk-throsters : shewing their misery, and the cause thereof, and what will only cure both them and the evils England's trade groans under, and other English manufacturers, from the like desolation : in a letter to a member of the Honourable House of Commons.</title>
            <author>A. N.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52642</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R474</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12409300</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12409300</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61473</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52642)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61473)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 284:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England's advocate, Europe's monitor being an intreaty for help in behalf of the English silk-weavers and silk-throsters : shewing their misery, and the cause thereof, and what will only cure both them and the evils England's trade groans under, and other English manufacturers, from the like desolation : in a letter to a member of the Honourable House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>A. N.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 3-56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Larkin, Jun., and are to be sold by J. Nut ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: A.N.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in University of Chicago Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Silk manufacturers --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Silk industry --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61473:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61473:1"/>
            <p>England's Advocate, EUROPE'S MONITOR: BEING An Intreaty FOR HELP, In Behalf of the Engliſh <hi>Silk-Weavers</hi> AND <hi>Silk-Throſters</hi> SHEWING Their <hi>Miſery,</hi> and the <hi>Cauſe</hi> thereof; And what will only <hi>Cure</hi> both Them and the Evils <hi>England</hi>'s Trade groans under, and other Engliſh Manufacturers, from the like Deſolation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a LETTER to a Member of the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Houſe of Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>George Larkin,</hi> Jun. and are to be Sold by <hi>J. Nut,</hi> near <hi>Stationers Hall.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:61473:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61473:2"/>
            <head>ENGLAND's Advocate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In a <hi>LETTER</hi> to an Honourable Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">(1.) YOurs of the 20th paſt, acquaints me that you have lately rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a diſmal Account of the <hi>Decay of Trade;</hi> and partic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of the <hi>Silk Manufacture of England,</hi> and the <hi>Deplorable Poverty</hi> of the generality of Perſons concerned in it, and related to it, which you ſay is ſo ſtartling and amazing, that you cannot but call in queſtion the Sincerity of the Relator, and the Truth of his Narration: And therefore you earneſtly deſire me, of whoſe Integrity and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, you are pleaſed to ſay, you make no doubt, that I wou'd deal fully and freely with you, in declaring what Truth there is in it; and if any, then what may be the Cauſes thereof, and what Remedies I think may be proper for it. Now though I queſtion my own Ability for ſo great an Undertaking, yet I cannot altogether deny ſo good a Friend; and if I ſhou'd fail in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you the expected Satisfaction, yet I will never deceive you with Falſhood, but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61473:3"/> according to the beſt of my knowledge and skill, ſhall act impartially, as one who has only the Common and True Intereſt of his Countrey in his Eye: And herein I ſhall reſtrain my ſelf chiefly to the <hi>Weaving Trades</hi> in and about the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Canterbury,</hi> of which my many years Experience will not ſuffer me to be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; not doubting but that <hi>Norwich, Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol,</hi> and other Trading Places, will ſpeak loudly for themſelves, as having too juſt Cauſe: And I heartily thank both you and all thoſe worthy Members, who you ſay are willing to Relieve us, but heartily ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that it cannot be done at preſent; the ſtate of Affairs being ſuch at this inſtant time, that if the Petition of the <hi>Weaver</hi>'s <hi>Company</hi> had been Received, it could have done them no preſent kindneſs. But ſince you tell me, That if I can give you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Satisfaction, you will communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it to others, who may be capable of doing us ſome good Service ere long, I will adventure to try what can be done.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The <hi>Weavers</hi> and <hi>Silk and Mohair Throſters of London,</hi> are ſo very Numerous a Company, that according as they flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh or fail, moſt other <hi>Trades</hi> feel the good or ill Effects of it; and they are of two ſorts, either the <hi>Maſters</hi> or <hi>Fabricators,</hi> or elſe the <hi>Workmen</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> being far the greater Number, and in which are to be included multitudes of <hi>Women</hi> and <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61473:3"/> for they are Trades which employ variety of hands, and enables even <hi>Children,</hi> at leaſt in part, to get their Livelihood, to the great Relief, Eaſe and Comfort of their <hi>poor Parents.</hi> And here, if I cou'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſighing remember the Bleſſings of Peace and good Management, I ſhould tell you, That from the Reſtoration of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to the beginning of the preſent Revolution, this profitable and neceſſary <hi>Broad-Weaving Trade</hi> was increaſed 19 parts in 20, to what it was before. And altho the Foundation of our Deſolation, which was before (as 'tis ſaid) by Br——y attain'd, began its Effects towards the end of that Kings Reign, and that vaſt quantities of <hi>India</hi> Wrought Silks were brought over, it was chiefly to the prejudice of the Woollen Manufacture, for then the better ſort of Women ſcorn'd them, and they were moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed inſtead of Serges, Tammies, and <hi>Norwich</hi> Stuffs: But that produc'd ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Effects, that the Growth of ſeveral Years Wooll lay to Moth-eat, till that happy and Ingenious Invention of both Silk and Worſted Crapes, gave new Life both to the Wooll and Silk Manufactory, (for Burying in Woollen would not do it) and rendered the <hi>Indian</hi> Silks and Stuffs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible to all ſorts of People, and to the Advantage of all parts and places where it was ſetled; whereby great multitudes of other <hi>Trades</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> who had their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61473:4"/> thereon, proſpered and lived well; many Fields were turned into Streets, and Houſes Let, before they could be finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and multitudes of Strangers were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, and had full Employment in the <hi>Weaving-Trade; the Brewer, the Baker, the Butcher, the Victualler,</hi> were well paid; and that I am ſure could be no damage to the <hi>Landlord;</hi> and the Nation abounded with <hi>Men and Money,</hi> in which two things, with God's Bleſſing, the main <hi>Strength</hi> of a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> conſiſts.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) But alas! we may now ſay with the Brazen Head, <hi>Time Was:</hi> For Now there is ſuch an utter Decay of Trade, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the <hi>Weaving Part,</hi> and its De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendancies, that a <hi>Maſter,</hi> who formerly employed <hi>Twenty, Thirty,</hi> or more, cannot now employ <hi>Four,</hi> nor find them full work: The reſt are put to miſerable ſhifts, and at beſt they are forced to take up with <hi>ſpare Diet,</hi> and <hi>the worſt of Proviſions,</hi> and that many times <hi>not very wholeſome;</hi> and to purchaſe <hi>This,</hi> they are fain to ſtrip their Houſes, and ſell the Furniture by degrees, till from one thing after another, it comes to the very <hi>Bed</hi> they lie on, and they are reduc'd to a wad of ſtraw for their Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a few ſhavings for a neceſſary fire, to boyl a little Water-gruel, or a Beaſts Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and when all is ſpent, then the upper Garments, if worth any thing, goe to the <hi>Broker,</hi> for a ſmall pittance of Money, to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61473:4"/> get a little Recruits for Belly-Timber; and thus ſtarved inſide and outſide, they ſpin out a miſerable Life, faintly walking, all Tatter'd and Torn, more like <hi>Ghoſts and Shadows</hi> than <hi>Living Men and Women,</hi> till being able no longer to hold out againſt Weakneſs and Want, they drop into their Graves: And tho' the Weekly Bills may call it <hi>Conſumptions, Convulſions,</hi> or by other ſuch Artificial Names, yet if the <hi>Searchers</hi> wou'd ſpeak out, or your Worſhip wou'd ſummon a <hi>Jury</hi> of <hi>Church-Wardens</hi> and <hi>Overſeers of the Poor,</hi> from <hi>Algate, Biſhopſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, Cripple-gate, Shoreditch, Stepny,</hi> S. <hi>Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and <hi>Southwark,</hi> with the Precincts and Hamlets thereunto belonging, I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent they would bring in their Verdict, That no ſmall number of them dyed of a <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> in plain Engliſh called <hi>Starving.</hi> And this is the more to be lamented, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it befalls the better and honeſter ſort of them: for thoſe, whoſe <hi>modeſty</hi> will not let them <hi>beg,</hi> nor <hi>their honeſty</hi> ſuffer them <hi>to ſteal,</hi> when they can find nothing to ſet their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry</hi> at work, their <hi>hearts</hi> ſink, they hide their <hi>heads</hi> for grief and ſhame, and ſo pine away with want: And thus thoſe Men are loſt, who wou'd improve Trade, and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding profitable to the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) To this you may add the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the many Houſes which ſtand empty in theſe and ſuch-like Places, which formerly were crowded with two or three
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61473:5"/> Families: And as for many Houſes which are inhabited, they are ſuffered ſo to be, rather to prevent the heavy payment of three or four ſhillings Tax in the pound, falling on the Landlord, than for any hope of more Rent he hath from the Tenant: Nay, I know ſome who would gladly loſe their Houſes, would the grand Landlord accept and acquit them. Perhaps you will think it ſtrange, if I ſhould ſay, I know the Men that are Ruin'd and Undone, by having whole Ranges of Houſes given them, only for being become bound to pay ſome Ground-Rent, that was covenanted for before the Building; and yet of this kind, you may eaſily be inform'd of divers inſtances, in the <hi>Tower-Ham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lets,</hi> and <hi>New Town;</hi> and notwithſtanding all this Loſs and Deſolation, yet within a few years in thoſe places, they have been forced to double their Rates for the <hi>Poor;</hi> and when that would not do, then to add an Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Rate of Six Months to the year; and ſome Pariſhes, that were hundreds of pounds before-hand ſome years ſince, are now run deep in debt, with endeavouring to ſupport their Poor, and to prevent this miſerable Poverty growing upon us; and all to no purpoſe; for never did the Poor ſwarm at that rate as now, and ſtill daily increaſe; ſo that no Man can have a ſpare Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thing to give away, but once in an hour he ſhall have three or four aſſaulting
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61473:5"/> his houſe with doleful complaints to beg it, and things grow daily ſo from bad to worſe, that in a little time we may fear to ſee <hi>begging and ſtealing</hi> to become the <hi>two</hi> moſt <hi>general Profeſſions or Employments</hi> in the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and if there be no remedy for theſe things, or none will be taken, we ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ere long from the moſt <hi>flouriſhing Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> become the moſt <hi>deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble People</hi> under the Cope of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">(5.) I fear I have ſurfeited you with Complaints; but that I may now afford you a handle, whereby you may do your Country ſome good ſervice, of which I know you ſo zealouſly deſirous, that you never ſpared any honeſt Pains which might tend to produce that Effect, I ſhall now lay before you, what I apprehend to be the <hi>principal Cauſes</hi> of this daily encreaſing <hi>Poverty and Miſery;</hi> and that conſideration in courſe will direct to the <hi>Remedies:</hi> But before I come to the ſtanding Cauſes among our ſelves; I ſhall take notice of one thing, which I take to be an accidental Cauſe, and yet a great preſent furtherance of this Miſchief, and that is the free Admiſſion of ſo many <hi>French, Walloons,</hi> and other <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners</hi> amongſt us: Not that I againſt all <hi>Foreigners,</hi> much leſs againſt the <hi>Relief</hi> of Men in <hi>diſtreſs,</hi> of which I am confident you will bear me witneſs; but I think our <hi>Charity</hi> to others might be ſo managed, as not to be <hi>uncharitable</hi> to our ſelves. For
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61473:6"/> many complain, that they enjoy ſeveral <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities and Priviledges</hi> more than the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> themſelves, which is grating, provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and uneaſie: And they alſo urge the large Contributions from time to time made to them, which I ſhould never grudge, but that I find this uſe to be made of them, by the help thereof to work un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Heads</hi> of their own <hi>Party</hi> at lower Rates, than the <hi>Engliſh</hi> could, at the rate Proviſions now are; and by this means they got the <hi>Work</hi> out of their <hi>Hands,</hi> and the <hi>Bread</hi> out of their <hi>Mouths:</hi> And ſo long as thoſe Contributions laſted, they did, and would hold it; but now they fail, I am informed that ſeveral of them think of tranſplanting themſelves into other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; and ſo doubtleſs will the <hi>Engliſh</hi> too, rather than ſtarve at home (but I fear <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> cannot afford them Relief) for Trade will run thither, where it meets with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and ſits eaſie; and at this rate the <hi>Nation</hi> will be in danger to be much <hi>diſpeopled</hi> as well as <hi>impoveriſhed;</hi> which can bode no good, if not wiſely preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) But that we may come more cloſe to the matter; the Deſign of <hi>Trade</hi> is to ſupply our <hi>want,</hi> and encreaſe our <hi>wealth,</hi> and therefore ought to be managed to thoſe ends: But if it multiply our <hi>Inconveniences,</hi> or exhauſt our <hi>Riches,</hi> ſuch Trading is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Poſt to ruine, and therefore a ſpeedy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61473:6"/> ſtop ought to be put to it: For this reaſon let Men talk what they pleaſe of a <hi>free Trade, and leaving it uncircumſcribed,</hi> they muſt at laſt allow it to be limited by ſuch Rules and Maximes, as may make it <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial</hi> and not <hi>hurtful</hi> to a <hi>Nation;</hi> but to ſet them, ſo as to make them obligatory and effectual, belongs to Authority, where I leave them, and proceed to make good my Promiſe.</p>
            <p n="7">(7.) And here, I cannot but take notice of one miſtake, which multitudes of well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning Perſons make; for whereas it hath been wiſely provided, that our own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities ſhould be manufactured at home, many have thought, that by wearing <hi>fine Engliſh Cloth,</hi> they were the great <hi>Conſumers</hi> of <hi>Engliſh VVool,</hi> which is a great Errour: For it hath been proved more than once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that no Cloth of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 10 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard white, or 13 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard in mixt Colours, ſold at <hi>Blackwell-Hall,</hi> hath one Drachm of <hi>Engliſh VVool</hi> therein, unleſs by Accident, and ſo all the better ſort become only the Conſumers of the <hi>Socove or Spaniſh VVool;</hi> and by this means <hi>Hair-Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blets, Prunello's, Callaminco's, Velvets, Silks,</hi> and ſuch like wearing, hath been, and is much diſuſed, for the purchaſing the Materials, (whereof they were here made,) our own <hi>Cloth-Manufactures</hi> were in great quantities exported, and to which a great ſtop by that means is made; ſo that hereby a double
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61473:7"/> Manufacture is diſcouraged, and a double Gain to the Nation loſt: For he that wears a <hi>Hair-camblet Coat or Cloak, or Prunello-gown,</hi> or any ſort of <hi>Hair</hi> or <hi>Silk, Velvet</hi> or <hi>Shag,</hi> is in the effect a more true <hi>Conſumer of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Wooll,</hi> than he that wears <hi>Cloth; Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grain,</hi> or <hi>Mohair Yarn,</hi> of which the aforeſaid Commodities are made, being generally the <hi>Product</hi> or <hi>Exchange</hi> of our <hi>Courſeſt Engliſh Woollen Cloth,</hi> by which Vend the <hi>Clothier</hi> is encouraged; and the preparing the Yarn, which comes in for it, gives a great and comfortable Employment to vaſt Numbers of People in the ſeveral Manufactures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: And before this War, we had attained to that Perfection, as not only to ſerve our ſelves in Hair-Camblets, which before uſed to be ſent us from <hi>Bruſſels</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> but had gained ſuch a Preference, as to ſerve the wiſeſt <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>French Merchants,</hi> where and to other parts, we had a very profitable Trade, in the former times. I could not ſay leſs, to undeceive many, who did not underſtand how by this means the <hi>Silk</hi> and <hi>Mohair-Yarn-Trade,</hi> is much impaired, and <hi>Engliſh Cloathing</hi> it ſelf damnified, which is one, tho' no great cauſe, of this <hi>Deplorable Poverty.</hi> Nor wou'd I be thought, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of this Miſtake, to undervalue the home Conſumption of our own Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Manufacture.</p>
            <p n="8">(8.) As to what you hint in relation to the <hi>War,</hi> the late ill State of our <hi>Coin,</hi> and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61473:7"/> the preſent <hi>Dearneſs of Silk,</hi> I am confident that they have had very little Influence in this matter; and that if the <hi>publick good</hi> of the Kingdom in general had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the particular and <hi>private In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> of a few ſelf-deſigning Perſons, the firſt and laſt of theſe had rather been to the Advantage of the Silk Manufactures both <hi>Weavers and Throſters,</hi> with all their Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, than to their Detriment. For ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aſide the <hi>Act</hi> prohibiting Silk com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but by long Sea in the Time of <hi>War,</hi> I am confident, that I can convince you and all reaſonable and unbyaſſed Men, that the <hi>War</hi> would have been greatly to our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; and the Scarcity of Mony might have been ſupplied by Credit for that time, had it not been ruined by other means. The dearneſs of Silk, if it be ſo in all other parts, hurts the Trade no more than ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Cheapneſs would: But to inſiſt on theſe things, as I might, would ſwell my Diſcourſe beyond my deſign; and therefore I ſhall proceed with all poſſible Brevity to what I am confident is the bane of the <hi>Silk Manufactures</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and in the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of it, of the <hi>Woollen</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p n="9">(9.) The unreaſonable and indiſcreet Preference of <hi>India Manufactures,</hi> whereby ſo vaſt a <hi>Manufactory</hi> and Profit is carried from us thither, eſpecially of that of <hi>India Silks and Stuffs,</hi> hath almoſt wholly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown and unhinged this profitable and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61473:8"/> neceſſary <hi>Trade</hi> of <hi>Silk throwing and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> by which vaſt Multitudes of People of both Sexes young and old lately lived com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably, and ſo did all its dependants. Firſt in the winding it raw, whereby Thouſands of Seamens Wives and Children, and other People many Miles round the City (who now ſtarve) earned their Bread, to perfect it for the <hi>Throſter;</hi> to ſpin which again af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded a good livelihood to thoſe that dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ſame to be thrown for the <hi>Weavers</hi> Uſe, after the <hi>Dyers</hi> have gained their live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood by Dying it. <hi>The Winders, Warpers, Quillers, Draw-Boys,</hi> had good ſubſiſtance by their Attendance on Weavers, (beſides other Trades, as Harneſs-makers, Turners, Loom-makers, Reed-makers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) twenty, thirty, or forty of which <hi>Weavers</hi> uſed to be employed by one <hi>Fabricator,</hi> which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers many of them have now nothing to do, but are driven to this miſerable Choice, either to <hi>beg, ſteal, or ſtarve.</hi> And before this proſperous Trade was ruined, every Maſter according to his Stock and Credit, provided before-hand for a <hi>Spring Trade,</hi> and was certain of a Market in <hi>February</hi> or <hi>March,</hi> had he never ſo many hundred pounds worth of Goods by him; and the whole Summer following all hands work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing early and late were little enough to ſupply the <hi>Mercers;</hi> though many that had good foreſight, and large Stocks and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, would then be providing a freſh Stock
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61473:8"/> of Goods proper for <hi>Winter VVare,</hi> for which about <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term they failed not to find ſale; and by this means the <hi>whole Cloathing Trade</hi> of <hi>England</hi> was upheld, (which now ſinks) The <hi>Turky and Italian Merchants</hi> ſending our Coth, Serges, Bays, Says, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to <hi>Turky</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> for Silk to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy theſe numerous People, who lived up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and expended the Productions of our own Land; and whether the very Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and Return of their ſeveral Cargo's in our Coaſting Trade to ſupply them, be not of more advantage even to our <hi>Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation,</hi> than the <hi>Eaſt-India Trade,</hi> I leave to their Judgments, who ſhall conſider, that this laſt ſerves chiefly to deſtroy our moſt <hi>skilful Seamen,</hi> which their former Employments from <hi>New-Caſtle, Cheſter,</hi> and other parts, had made; it being too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently obſerved, that ſcarce half the Ship's Crew comes ſafe again to <hi>England,</hi> that ſet out from thence for the Eaſt-<hi>Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">(10.) This great <hi>inconvenience,</hi> or rather <hi>miſchief,</hi> was firſt brought on us about 30 years ſince by the <hi>Eaſt-India Company's</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding over ſeveral of our Engliſh <hi>skilful VVeavers, Dyers, and Pattern-drawers,</hi> &amp;c. to inſtruct the <hi>Indians</hi> in ſuch Methods as ſuited the <hi>European Fancies;</hi> before which time, all things they ſent were contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the <hi>Ladies</hi> thought them ſcarce good enough for their <hi>Kitchin-Maids;</hi> but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61473:9"/> now ſo eſteem them, that our <hi>Silk Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factury</hi> at home is on the brink of deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>England</hi> it ſelf will next feel it, and all <hi>Europe</hi> too, if they be no wiſer to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it, as I ſhall now endeavour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate.</p>
            <p n="11">(11.) The <hi>Advocates</hi> for our <hi>Eaſt-India Trade</hi> are pleaſed at all times, to extol and magnifie <hi>Merchandize</hi> and <hi>Navigation,</hi> as the Foundation of our <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> and doubtleſs they are very likely to maintain it, who take the Courſe to leave us nothing in the end to <hi>Merchandize</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; for what better can be expected from them, who carry away our <hi>Money,</hi> and deſtroy our <hi>Manufactures?</hi> And therefore theſe eloquent Gentlemen ought to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that a due <hi>improvement</hi> of our <hi>own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions</hi> by Labour and Induſtry, was the <hi>Foundation</hi> of our <hi>Merchandize,</hi> and ſtill muſt <hi>ſupport</hi> it, or it will fail in time, as alſo our <hi>Lands</hi> will ſink in <hi>value,</hi> and the <hi>Nation</hi> be <hi>diſpeopled;</hi> and for this reaſon by great Miſtake was the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> lately obliged to export yearly a 100000 <hi>l</hi>'s worth of our <hi>VVoollen Manufactures,</hi> which impoſition proved as <hi>unprofitable</hi> to us, as it was <hi>unnatural</hi> in it ſelf: For they cannot ſell <hi>Cloth</hi> in thoſe Places, whence they bring thoſe ready wrought <hi>Silks,</hi> which deſtroy our <hi>Manufactury</hi> at home, but were forced to vend it at thoſe Markets where the <hi>Turky Merchants</hi> had otherwiſe ſent it,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61473:9"/> and ſo became a hindrance to their Trade, which is more profitable to us; and when they impoſed the wearing of <hi>Woollen</hi> on their <hi>Souldiers</hi> under Penalty of loſing their <hi>Pay,</hi> I am credibly inform'd, that they could never bring them to it, unleſs on <hi>Pay-days,</hi> and then not without grumbling, the heat of the Country making them unable to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it. Now let it be conſidered, that the Management of our <hi>Lands and Sheep</hi> produceth that <hi>VVool,</hi> which after by the Labour and Induſtry of divers <hi>Manufacturers</hi> (too many to be particularly named) is wonderfully improved; and while they are doing that, wear our <hi>courſer VVool</hi> and <hi>Leather,</hi> ſpend our Butter, Cheeſe, Corn, by which many others are maintained a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> home, and by the Product of their labours Navigation maintained abroad: For their improvements in ſeveral Parts are in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Cargo's ſent to <hi>Turky, Italy, Spain,</hi> and other Parts, whereof part returns in <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrought Silk,</hi> and other neceſſary Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, part in <hi>Silver</hi> from <hi>Cadiz,</hi> which the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> put a ſtop to, and ſend it away to the <hi>great Mogul</hi> to bring home thoſe Commodities, which if prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not only ruines all thoſe <hi>Manufacturies</hi> of <hi>Wool,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Turky and Italian Trade,</hi> which in return of thoſe Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, brought hither <hi>Raw Silk;</hi> and this they do by bringing over their vaſt Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go's of ready <hi>wrought Silk</hi> from <hi>India,</hi> in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61473:10"/> lieu of our good hard <hi>Silver</hi> and <hi>Gold,</hi> which is ſure to return to our uſe no more, than the Woollen wherein we bury our Dead. This done, their Cargo's are expos'd on their Stage at St. <hi>Hellens,</hi> where our Females are charm'd, and fall ſo deſperately in love with them, that no other form or manner of Silk than what they <hi>laſt brought,</hi> muſt be the <hi>Standard</hi> of our <hi>Mode and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion;</hi> ſo that when our <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury Weavers</hi> againſt the Spring-trade, have provided many Thouſand pounds worth of <hi>Luſtrings, Tabby's,</hi> and other as good Silks as the World can afford, in comes an <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Ship freight with <hi>Dammask</hi> and <hi>Sattins,</hi> which being expoſed on their Stage, makes the <hi>Mode</hi> for that Spring; and the <hi>Engliſh Fabricators</hi> muſt keep that years Goods, or ſell them to vaſt loſs, and then are conſtrained with vaſt Coſts and Charges to alter their <hi>Faſhion</hi> for the next year, when in comes more <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Ships with Goods of quite ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther form, and all the <hi>Weavers</hi> are in the dirt again: And thus for ſeveral years have the <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Canterbury Weavers</hi> been diſappointed, and Numbers of them undone, to the utmoſt Degree of Poverty; and many of them not getting any Sale for their Goods thus provided, at ſo little as 25, or 30, or more <hi>per Cent,</hi> loſs, have left off, and fallen into the <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſted Weavers;</hi> and I doubt not but that famous Corporation
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61473:10"/> and City of <hi>Norwich,</hi> has and will feel the ill Effects of it: For the <hi>London Weavers</hi> not being tyed to thoſe Rules and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, which the <hi>Norwich Weavers,</hi> for the Credit of the Kingdom and themſelves, had obliged their Members to, for making Goods free from Deceit, (as the <hi>Colobeſter Bays-makers</hi> do) have in part juſtled them out of their Trade, by being thus at their liberty: But now <hi>Norwich</hi> for its own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation having taken off that reſtraint, (which otherwiſe had been commendably kept on) <hi>Spittle-fields</hi> will not be able to maintain that <hi>Trade,</hi> which at beſt here, is but a <hi>ſtarving</hi> one, to the poor <hi>Workmen;</hi> and therefore <hi>Norwich</hi> having ſet her Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers at liberty, <hi>Spittle-fields</hi> Workmen muſt in a ſhort time beg, ſtarve, or be kept by the Pariſh.</p>
            <p n="12">(12.) This is a ſad, but true Hiſtory of the <hi>decay</hi> and <hi>miſery</hi> of the <hi>weaving Trade,</hi> which is partly cauſed by the ſelf-endedneſs, and pernicious Trading of ſome particular Merchants; partly by the vain and fond, I am unwilling to ſay vitious Humour, of the Females. For the <hi>Mercers</hi> dare not buy any thing conſiderable, but what is <hi>Indian,</hi> or what he muſt pretend to be ſo; and who can blame him for dealing therein, when otherwiſe the <hi>Draper,</hi> as things ſtand, would deprive him of his Trade? And now they cannot but confeſs, that their great care is how to provide good ſtore of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:61473:11"/> an <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Sale; and if in the Intervals they ſpare any, it is to buy the <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Pains</hi> of the <hi>Weaver</hi> for little or nothing, and ſometimes part of the <hi>Silk</hi> into the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. And I aſſure you, Sir! it almoſt makes my Blood chill to think, that the beſt of our <hi>Fabricator</hi>'s buſineſs (that little they now do) is ſo to <hi>counterfeit</hi> the <hi>Indians,</hi> that the <hi>Mercer</hi> may vouch it for ſuch with confidence.</p>
            <p n="13">(13.) But this matter is accounted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with many; and they commonly ſay, That the <hi>Silk Weaving and Throwing,</hi> with all its Dependants, had better be deſtroyed, than the <hi>Eaſt India Trade</hi> obſtructed or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judic'd: <hi>For</hi> (ſay they) <hi>though they do ſend great ſtore of</hi> Money <hi>away to purchaſe the</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Silks and Toys, <hi>yet they bring great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to the Nation, by returning back Money from moſt other</hi> European Countreys, <hi>and ſo the Nation is by them enriched.</hi> In anſwer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, though I have much to ſay againſt the Truth of this, yet at preſent I will not quarrel with any of their Importations or Exportations, as ſuch, let their Trade be as great as they can deſire; though I am ſure in the end it will prove much to the Prejudice of <hi>Europe</hi> in general, and more eſpecially to us; but that which I now complain of, is the home conſumption of thoſe Manufactures, which will inevitably deſtroy not only our <hi>Silk,</hi> but our <hi>VVoollen Manufactures:</hi> And that I may commend
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61473:11"/> you to a compleat Judge in this Caſe, Pray read the Eſſay upon the <hi>Indian Trade,</hi> whom I take to be the beſt <hi>Advocate</hi> for that <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> this Age hath afforded, and I ſuppoſe he may have been as well paid for it: It is pity ſo fine a Pen ſhou'd be employ'd in ſo bad a Cauſe; but for his ingenious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of that Truth, which if rightly conſidered gives it up, we may forgive him. And thus ſaith he, p. 12. <hi>As to the Eaſt-India Trade in general, if all would by common Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent agree to have no further dealing to thoſe Parts, this ſide of the World by ſuch Reſolution would certainly ſave a great and continual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Treaſure; for that</hi> Europe <hi>draws from thence nothing of ſolid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, Materials to ſupply Luxury, and only periſhable Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſends thither Gold and Silver, which is buried there, and never returns.</hi> And then p. 13. concludes, <hi>I cannot find what is become of the 800 Millions digg'd out of the Earth, unleſs 150 Millions of it be carry'd away and ſunk in the Eaſt Indies.</hi> A very fair Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the true matter of Fact! And who are the Fools? As for <hi>Spain</hi> and other Countries, who manufacture not what they uſe, they may with ſome colour of Reaſon be indifferent in their Preference; but for us to do it, and ſet the World an Example ſo to do, is no better than Folly, if not Madneſs; who for the love of <hi>India Manufactured Silks, Tinder Calico's</hi> and <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlins,</hi> throw away our <hi>Gold and Silver,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61473:12"/> to be recovered, when we might have good <hi>Cambrick</hi> and <hi>Lawns,</hi> and other <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Linnen,</hi> and <hi>Raw Silk</hi> to employ our People, in exchange for our <hi>Woollen Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures;</hi> which becauſe we will not, we loſe both our Trade and our Money, which we might keep at home, or ſend abroad to better purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="15">(15.) O but, ſays this and other <hi>Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> Advocates, <hi>Money is but a Commodity, and Trade muſt not be circumſcribed but free:</hi> That by their bringing <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Silks and Stuffs cheap for our own uſe, we may find other Markets for our Manufactures abroad. But why then ſuch a buſtle and flouriſh at other Times, when contending for the Ballance of Trade with the <hi>European Countries?</hi> But I grant that <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver</hi> is but a <hi>Commodity,</hi> which we ought to be willing to part with, when there is a good cauſe for it: But then it ought to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd what kind of Commodity it is; it is the <hi>Sinews</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> and the <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Trade,</hi> without which, Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men cannot well be employ'd; the more any <hi>Nation</hi> hath of it, the more <hi>Wealthy</hi> and more <hi>Powerful</hi> it is; the <hi>leſs</hi> they have, ſo much the more <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>inconſiderable</hi> they are; ſo that to let our <hi>Money</hi> go from us, is to part not only with our <hi>Wealth,</hi> but our <hi>Strength.</hi> Beſides, <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver</hi> is not a <hi>Commodity</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Growth;</hi> if we make the <hi>Fleece</hi> into Cloth, and ſend it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61473:12"/> away, the Sheep affords us another Fleece the next year; but ſend our <hi>Money</hi> away, and none comes up here in the room of it: And when other Nations have it, they bid it welcome, and are unwilling to let it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again; and therefore the ſafeſt courſe is to make it ſtay at home, unleſs when our own real advantage, neceſſity, or ſafety re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the contrary; and therefore ſome have compared it to the Blood in the Body; or rather the Spirits in the Blood; waſting makes us languiſh, great exhauſting kills. But that you may more plainly ſee the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, pray obſerve, that if <hi>Money</hi> be but a <hi>Commodity,</hi> ſo is <hi>fine China Ware</hi> alſo, and being we can do ſuch fine things with worſe Fools than our ſelves, ſuppoſe for once we ſhould ſend all our Contemptible Cupboards of <hi>Plate,</hi> with all our other <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver</hi> to the <hi>Indies,</hi> and have it returned in <hi>Delicate China Ware,</hi> either for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> or <hi>Trade,</hi> ſhould we not be mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly enrich'd? For Fancies ſake, I will relate a ſtory, which I long ſince receiv'd for Truth, when I little thought of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this occaſion to uſe it: The Lady of a Worſhipful Knight, Sir <hi>R. K.</hi> of <hi>E</hi>—oblig'd him to make her a return of 100 <hi>l.</hi> in this pretty Commodity, with which ſhe finely adorned her Cloſet, under the Window of which was an Out-houſe, and ſhe keeping a pretty Pug, and going abroad in her Coach without him, up skips th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:61473:13"/> Monkey from the Wall to the Top of the Out-houſe, and the Lady having left her Cloſet-Caſement open, in he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, and admiring how prettily it rang and tinkled, as he jumbled them together, he never left off the Frolick, till he brought it all to its Intrinſick Value. Sir, I ſhall leave the Application to your ſelf; only I think I may ſay, That the <hi>Conſumers of Indian Silks</hi> are much as profitable to the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as <hi>Pug</hi> was to his <hi>Lady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">(16.) It's commonly ſaid, <hi>That far fetcht and dear bought, is good for Ladies;</hi> nor do I envy them any <hi>Finery,</hi> provided it be not purchaſed with the <hi>Ruine</hi> of their <hi>Country:</hi> But when they ſhall conſider that by theſe means their Husbands <hi>Rents</hi> muſt <hi>fall,</hi> the Uſeful and Profitable <hi>Trades</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <hi>fail,</hi> and their <hi>Countrey</hi> be <hi>Diſpeopled</hi> by Death, or neceſſitating the Inhabitants to flock to other Places, where they can get a Livelihood, and all this to <hi>inrich</hi> a far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Inſidel Countrey,</hi> by <hi>impoveriſhing</hi> our ſelves, I hope they will grow ſo wiſe and good humour'd, as to part with one Piece of Vanity, which is ſo pernicious.</p>
            <p n="17">(17.) And further, if this be not the effect of that <hi>Devouring Trade,</hi> how comes it to paſs, that <hi>Silver</hi> is <hi>5d. per</hi> ounce more worth than <hi>Money,</hi> only to be ſent to the <hi>Indies</hi> to be buried, and <hi>Cadiz</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> and all Places, dreined to obtain it on any Conditions, but that the <hi>Nation</hi> muſt be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61473:13"/> 
               <hi>ruined</hi> to enrich a few Men by management of a <hi>free Trade,</hi> as they are ready always to call it, when we talk of any, tho' never ſo needful, Prohibiting of never ſo ſmall a Branch of it? But I think this <hi>free Trade</hi> to be a Contradiction, as matters were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged.</p>
            <p n="18">(18.) If you pleaſe throughly to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Management of this <hi>Eaſt-India Trade,</hi> you will be forced to acknowledge, That had we not ſent <hi>Indian Linnen</hi> upon the <hi>Scots,</hi> to the great detriment of their <hi>Scotch-Cloth-Trade,</hi> (the principal Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of that Kingdom) it is believed they never would have thought of an <hi>Eaſt-India Company,</hi> by which they hope to be even with us, by impoſing <hi>Indian Toys</hi> upon us by way of requital: And what detriment it will occaſion in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Affair, ſmall time will diſcover. And when other parts of <hi>Europe</hi> (which have not yet taken up that courſe) ſhall warily inſpect what we have been, and are now doing; Will they not think of ſetting up the ſame <hi>Trade,</hi> and impoſe their freight of <hi>Indian Goods</hi> upon us, as we have done upon them? only I can hardly think, that any but our ſelves, will be ſo indiſcreet, to ſend their Money Abroad, to the deſtruction of their Gainful <hi>Manufactures</hi> at Home, unleſs pure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge tempt them to it; that the ſame Trick may not be always plaid upon them, but that in requital, they may Trick o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61473:14"/> as well as they have done them: and I verily believe, that a few years will bring it to this paſs, and then we ſhall ſay, <hi>Who would have thought it?</hi> And when I conſider, how many <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndone Weavers,</hi> have ſet up <hi>Ale-Houſes,</hi> till they have had little Trade, except to tipple one with another, till they have <hi>broke themſelves</hi> again, and the <hi>Brewer</hi> into the bargain; it is to me an unlucky reſemblance, of what the <hi>European Trade</hi> in time muſt come to, when it is one King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with another, chiefly for <hi>Indian Geu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">(19.) Nor can there be any doubt, but that the Great <hi>Mogul</hi> and his People, when they obſerve the mad Eſteem we have for their Manufactures, will follow the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropean</hi> Examples, and advance their Prizes (as they have already done of late) and by laying on Great <hi>Duties,</hi> and Prohibiting <hi>Raw Silk,</hi> and <hi>Cotton Wool</hi> and <hi>Yarn,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially now they find they can have our Gold and Silver for it, ready Manufactured there; for the remedy of which, nothing but the Learned Doctors Obſervation before-cited, can give <hi>Europe</hi> an Effectual Cure: But would they agree together in an <hi>European</hi> Parliament, or Council, not to Conſume, or fetch any <hi>Indian Manufactures;</hi> this would perfectly cure the Evils the <hi>European Trades</hi> groan under; for the Remedying of which, it may be obſerved, how every Kingdom and Countrey hath ſtrugled to help them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61473:14"/> by <hi>unreaſonable Duties,</hi> and <hi>unnatural Prohibitions,</hi> upon one another; the effects of both which are, to <hi>impoveriſh</hi> all the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacturing People,</hi> though for the preſent, it may ſeem to enrich the <hi>Governing Part,</hi> yet it is all to the deſtruction of the <hi>European Trade;</hi> and we may ſtruggle our hearts out to relieve our Poor, for ſo long as this <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Gangreen</hi> is nouriſhed among us, nothing will Help, nothing will Do; becauſe the loſs of the Silk Manufactory in <hi>England,</hi> will certainly ſink the Exportation of the Woollen, in propo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, and render all Work-Houſes in Countries and Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Ineffectual, as does already appear.</p>
            <p n="20">(20.) Leſs matters, and even Trifles in reſpect of theſe, have Alarm'd our Fore-Fathers; yea, and have had ſome influence on our ſelves of late; I ſhall make at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, choice only of two inſtances, out of many, I mean the <hi>Dying,</hi> and the <hi>Button<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making Trade.</hi> For the benefit of the <hi>Dyers,</hi> and improving that <hi>Trade,</hi> it was enacted, That no <hi>Dyed Silk</hi> ſhould be <hi>Imported;</hi> and about the latter end of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, it was alſo by Law en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, That no <hi>Foreign-made Buttons</hi> ſhould be imported into <hi>England,</hi> with which our <hi>Dutch Friends</hi> before had plentifully ſerved us. And doth the <hi>Weavers</hi> and <hi>Weaving-Trade</hi> deſerve no Conſideration, which is Twenty times the value to the Kingdom more than both, and Employs more than
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61473:15"/> a hundred for one? And even the <hi>Button<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers</hi> have had the good fortune this very Seſſions, to be Relieved and Supported by this <hi>Truly Engliſh Parliament;</hi> for in conſideration of their Numbers, and Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they have ſecur'd them in their Trade, and that much to the Advantage of the <hi>Turkey Merchants:</hi> And though their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers at <hi>Macklesfield</hi> and <hi>Sherbourn,</hi> and the adjacent Countrey, are great, yet I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, I could name one Pariſh in <hi>London,</hi> wherein not many years ſince, before this ſad decay of Trade, <hi>the Weavers, Throſters, and their dependents,</hi> exceeded them all; How Numerous then would they be, if computed in all places? But the <hi>Button<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers</hi> may thank God, that they had not an <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> to cope with, and I am perſwaded, that could the <hi>Weavers,</hi> be ſecured againſt only the <hi>Engliſh</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of <hi>Figur'd, Stich'd, and Strip'd Eaſt-India Silks and Stuffs,</hi> they would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, and might be a Happy Proſperous People again, and both the <hi>Turkey and Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Merchants,</hi> Twenty times more bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitted, than by the <hi>Button Bill;</hi> and the Bleſſing would go round, for the Woollen Manufacture would feel the good effects of it; and leſs than this, can never preſerve them from total Ruine, in a ſhort time.</p>
            <p n="21">(21) And to ſay the Truth, our <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> ſome years ſince, were but little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to ſome back Friends, who when
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61473:15"/> they found they had too good a cauſe, and the <hi>Prohibiting Bill</hi> had paſs'd the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> perſwaded ſome, to gain a total Prohibition of all <hi>European</hi> Foreign-wrought Silks; for not having cauſe good enough fairly to Try it out with them, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed this way to hug them to Death, with that pretended kindneſs, and deſtroyed the <hi>Bill,</hi> by inſiſting on what is Unreaſonable: For if the <hi>Engliſh VVeaver</hi> cannot vie in <hi>Frugal Living, and Cheap Working,</hi> with thoſe Countreys, that purchaſe their <hi>Raw Silks,</hi> and <hi>Neceſſaries of Living,</hi> much at the ſame Rate themſelves do, they will then deſervedly ſuffer; but to oblige them to contend with a numerous multitude of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages</hi> that have their <hi>Silk</hi> to work upon for almoſt nothing, and want neither <hi>Fire</hi> nor <hi>Cloathing,</hi> while Two pence in Rice, will ſuſtain a Family of four or five for a week, is very hard meaſure, and unmerciful do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, unleſs ſuch methods are taken, as may reduce the value of Lands, and all its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions, to ſuch low Rates here, that they may work on an equal foot: But how cheap ſoever the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> may buy theſe Goods, <hi>England,</hi> and all its <hi>Ladies,</hi> ſhall and will pay dear enough for them, rather than go without them; ſo that unleſs they are by ſome means or other effectually Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd, <hi>England</hi> muſt be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndone</hi> to gratify a <hi>humour</hi> of <hi>vanity,</hi> and <hi>enrich</hi> a few, who care not who, nor how many they Ruine,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61473:16"/> ſo they may but Graſp all into their own hands; for otherwiſe one would think that the Productions of the Growth and Soil of <hi>India,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Pepper, Salt-Peter, Rice, Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-wool,</hi> and <hi>Yarn,</hi> and numbers more, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with what <hi>Wrought Silks</hi> they may export, might be ſufficient Gain, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Reaſonable Men; and as for <hi>Perſian Taffaties,</hi> and <hi>Plain</hi> Silks, the <hi>Weavers</hi> would not contend the matter.</p>
            <p n="22">(22) But to Prohibit the Wearing any thing, that may be Cheap Bought, which if the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> do, the Gain is to <hi>England,</hi> though they ſell never ſo dear to thoſe who Wear and Conſume it; which I take to be in the Body Politick, like over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorging with Meat and Drink in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body, which is weak and languid, and thrives not with it, unleſs in ſome great Wen, Excreſſency, or other Deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and if this be all we are to regard, it may as well hold good in other inſtances; and then let us ſuppoſe, that when our <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia-Sbips</hi> freight <hi>Bullion</hi> from <hi>Holland</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> they ſhould alſo there take in a good quantity of <hi>Spaniſh Wooll,</hi> and ſo ſave the Charge of bringing it to <hi>England,</hi> and then be ſure, not to forget to take along with them a few <hi>Worceſter-ſhire Cloth-weavers,</hi> and <hi>Cloth-workers,</hi> to inſtruct; and all ſorts of Work and Labour, being performed in <hi>India</hi> twelve times as Cheap as in <hi>England,</hi> and four Shillings worth of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61473:16"/> 
               <hi>Spaniſh-wool,</hi> making a yard of Cloth worth Fifteen Shillings, which at this Rate, will ſtand them but in Five Shillings, then there will be Ten Shilling ſaved for their Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and Profits, and ſo <hi>England</hi>'s the Gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and the Silver they may ſend to <hi>Bengal</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> for <hi>Raw Silk,</hi> to employ the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gul</hi>'s Subjects in other parts to work up, (as they already do) and ſo return back both the Cargoes of <hi>Silk</hi> and <hi>Cloth</hi> together, and at once disband all, both our <hi>Needleſs Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiers, and Silk Weavers;</hi> this will do the work effectually, and leave us nothing to do at home, which muſt certainly make us a Rich and Induſtrious People, or no Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at all conſiderable in a very little time: For I am ſure the project is not more ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, nor leſs pernicious in one reſpect, than the other. And where we are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to find this <hi>Market</hi> they talk of, for our own Manufactures, is little leſs than a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, and looks more like what the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar call a <hi>Vertuoſo-fancy</hi> than any <hi>poſſibility.</hi> For can we be ſo beſotted, as to imagine, that the World ſhould be become ſo <hi>fond</hi> of us, who are ſo <hi>Careleſs</hi> of our ſelves; that in ſpight of our Teeths, they ſhould be ſtudiers of, and induſtriouſly provide for our Good, by becoming Cuſtomers for our Manufactures, which we our ſelves ſlight and cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mn; or can it be thought reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to believe, that when we have brought our own <hi>Plantations,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards, and other
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61473:17"/> Places,</hi> to the uſe of <hi>Eaſt-India Silks, Cotten, Cloths</hi> and <hi>Stuffs</hi> (which our own great Preference and Eſteem, not only tends to, but effects) we ſhall ſtill have the better Markers abroad in ſome <hi>Newfound-Lands,</hi> or <hi>Countreys to be found out;</hi> where we may vend our <hi>Silks, Cloths, Bays, Serges, Perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana's, Norwich-Stuffs,</hi> and the like Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities; and it would be worth any Mans while, to get Information, what Market in this World, is not already fully ſtored and cloy'd with theſe Commodities, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe prepar'd by the <hi>Eaſt-India Traders,</hi> muſt go to the Prejudice of other more <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and Beneficial Merchants;</hi> unleſs they know how to carry them to the World in the Moon.</p>
            <p n="23">(23.) And if our Common Prints, do not Prevaricate, <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Venice</hi> have lately declared their ſenſe of this Evil, by a <hi>Prohibition of Indian Manufactures;</hi> and though the <hi>French King,</hi> for many years paſt, hath driven away ſo many thouſands of his <hi>poor Subjects</hi> to ſeek their Bread in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countreys, of which <hi>England</hi> hath entertained the greateſt part; and the moſt of thoſe that were <hi>Manufacturers,</hi> were no other way capable of earning their Living, but by the <hi>Weaving Trade;</hi> yet he hath manifeſted his conſtant care, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and afford a good Maintenance to thoſe that remain; as may appear, by his Edict of <hi>October</hi> 26. 1686. whereby he not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61473:17"/> only <hi>Prohibits</hi> the wearing of all ſorts of <hi>Eaſt-India Silks and Callico's,</hi> but alſo, under a ſevere Mulct, <hi>Prohibits</hi> the Imitation of their own made <hi>figured and flowred Silks by Printing;</hi> and commands their <hi>Prints</hi> and <hi>Tools</hi> to be <hi>Broke and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tterly Deſtroy'd:</hi> And in the laſt War, when they took and ſold many of our <hi>Eaſt-India Ships,</hi> they ſold not the <hi>Manufactured Goods,</hi> but under this Caution and Obligation, That they ſhould be again <hi>Exported:</hi> And by another Edict of —— 1694. For the Preſervation of the <hi>Button-makers Trade,</hi> He <hi>Prohibits</hi> the wear, or uſe, of <hi>Buttons,</hi> any other ways made, than with the <hi>Needle;</hi> and by all ways and means, endeavours that <hi>Bread,</hi> the ſtaff of Life, may be ſold <hi>Cheap.</hi> Now if we, to the great numbers of our <hi>own People,</hi> muſt, contrary to our former Laws, entertain and admit <hi>all Strangers</hi> that come, and give them right to work in our Trades, is it not high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unreaſonable to pour in upon us ſuch vaſt quantities of <hi>Indian Commodities,</hi> as deſtroy the <hi>Principal Manufactures;</hi> in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of which, both the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French Weavers</hi> muſt get their Bread, or Starve; whilſt at the ſame time we Prohibit <hi>Iriſh Cattle, Diſtil our Corn,</hi> and Export it too, if Cheap.</p>
            <p n="24">(24.) I cannot think ſuch like Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to be very conſiſtent with good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Policy, and muſt crave your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, if I tell you, That I believe this <hi>Eaſt-India
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61473:18"/> Trade</hi> of Goods <hi>there Manufactured,</hi> for our own Conſumption at home, is far more Prejudicial, not only to our own Silk <hi>Manufactures,</hi> but to <hi>England</hi> in general, than were thoſe <hi>wicked audacious Perſons,</hi> of whom ſo many were <hi>Hanged</hi> for <hi>Cliping and Coyning;</hi> for if they followed both Trades, and <hi>Coyned</hi> their <hi>Clipings,</hi> it was no loſs to <hi>England,</hi> for what we wanted in <hi>weight,</hi> we had in <hi>tale;</hi> and could we have paid there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our <hi>Foreign Bills,</hi> it would have been of greater advantage to <hi>England,</hi> than the <hi>Eaſt-India-Trade;</hi> but for thoſe <hi>Rogues</hi> who <hi>only clip'd,</hi> they deſerved a <hi>double Hanging,</hi> for they were one great Support of the <hi>Eaſt-India-Trade,</hi> their <hi>Meltings</hi> furniſhing them with <hi>Silver</hi> for a long time; the want of which now puts them to their ſhifts, and makes them pay ſo dear for it.</p>
            <p n="25">(25.) Thus, Sir, I have laid before you what I apprehend to be the Cauſes of this deſperate <hi>Decay</hi> of <hi>Trade,</hi> which will day by day more clearly appear, as our <hi>Poverty</hi> increaſeth; and hence the Remedies are viſible, if apply'd by a Powerful Hand. But becauſe you are urgent for my further Opinion herein, I ſhall point at ſome, tho' very briefly, they having been hinted at all along. It is an old and true Obſervation, <hi>That the knowledge of the Diſtemper is more than half the Cure;</hi> our Home-Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Eaſt-India ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Silks,</hi> is the Decay both of our <hi>Clothing and Silk Manufactures,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61473:18"/> the Weavers, Throſters,</hi> and all their <hi>Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants;</hi> and <hi>impoveriſheth</hi> all Places where thoſe <hi>Trades</hi> decay. But after the due <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement</hi> of our own <hi>Productions</hi> by <hi>Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures,</hi> as hath been already inſiſted on, A due Conſideration of that truly Noble <hi>Turkey Trade,</hi> is the next thing that can and will give us conſiderable Relief. Let only ſuch Encouragement be given, that thoſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> who ſpend their Youth in Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and to gain Experience in that Trade, and after venture Great Eſtates therein, when they return and ſettle here, and ſend others their <hi>Factors</hi> abroad, to do as they had done before them, may find a good Market, amongſt other their Commodities, for their <hi>Silk and Grogram Yarn,</hi> (which are the Principal Returns) and then the <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier</hi> and the <hi>Tin-Merchant</hi> ſhall never want a ſure <hi>Sale,</hi> and good <hi>Price</hi> for their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities; and I dare appeal to thoſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, whether any thing elſe can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this good effect; and be bold to ſay, That the Arts and Policy the <hi>French King</hi> is now making uſe of, to beat our <hi>Merchants</hi> out of that <hi>Trade,</hi> will do <hi>England</hi> more miſchief (if not prevented) than all our te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious War: For it is this inforceth many of them, for the employment of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, to ſtrike in with the <hi>Eaſt-India-Trade</hi> againſt their Judgments and Inclinations: For ſeeing we are reſolved to ruine our ſelves, they will come in for part of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61473:19"/> ſcramble. For 'tis plainly thus: The <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> can ſell nothing of Engliſh <hi>Silk,</hi> but with great loſs to <hi>Himſelf</hi> or the <hi>Weaver,</hi> and for this reaſon the <hi>Weavers</hi> are forced to deſiſt their <hi>Trade,</hi> the Silk lying on the Silkmens or Throſters hands, by which means the <hi>Merchant</hi> wants <hi>Sale,</hi> and ſhips away no more <hi>Cloth</hi> or <hi>Tin,</hi> and gives order to his <hi>Factor</hi> in <hi>Turkey,</hi> to forbear buying any more <hi>Silk,</hi> or <hi>Grograin,</hi> or <hi>Cotton-Yarn,</hi> whilſt the <hi>French</hi> buy up all, and give great encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and life to their <hi>Manufacturers</hi> at home; for want of which, our Trade is ſo deſtroy'd, that our Poor need not ſcoff at <hi>Wooden Shooes,</hi> for they muſt go <hi>Barefoot.</hi> I could give you ſeveral Links of the like Chain of Deſtruction to our <hi>Spaniſh, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Italian,</hi> and other <hi>Trades,</hi> whereby the other parts of our <hi>Woollen Manufactures</hi> (as <hi>Bays, Serges, Perpetuana's,</hi> and all ſorts of <hi>Norwich</hi> and other Stuffs) ſuffer the ſame Detriment from one and the ſame Cauſe. But ſure I am, the Caſe is extreamly alter'd with the Weavers, ſince <hi>Cannon-ſteeet</hi> both ſides the way was nothing but <hi>Weaver's Workſhops.</hi> But by what is before ſaid, it appears that making the <hi>Turkey-Trade</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous, wou'd in a great meaſure cure the Evil we groan under, and prevent their ſending their <hi>Silk</hi> and <hi>Grograin Yarn</hi> to <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which they are now neceſſitated to do for want of another Market. And I could
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61473:19"/> be content the fore-mentioned Author (tho' a profeſt <hi>Eaſt-India Advocate</hi>) might judge between us, for what valuable cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes theſe beneficial <hi>Merchants,</hi> as well as the <hi>Weavers,</hi> muſt be thus cramp'd and crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in their Trade; Which he aſſerts, p. 14. <hi>That Europe had been richer by a full Third Part than they are, if that Trade had never been Diſcovered or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaken; and that it bears hard only on thoſe Countreys that conſume thoſe Commodities.</hi> But for thoſe who will conſume them, to the deſtruction of their own valuable Productions and Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, and the carrying away all their Wealth in the end, I think they want a <hi>Lord have mercy upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">(26.) For my own part, I do not think but that the Departure of thoſe Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of <hi>Strangers</hi> would be a great detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the <hi>Turkey Traae,</hi> and that their abiding here might be of great advantage not only to that, but to <hi>England</hi> in general, if matters be ſo ordered that all may have Work: For multitudes of Induſtrious People are the beſt and ſureſt Riches and Strength of a Kingdom, if wiſely employ'd. For that in the Manufacturing of <hi>Grograin Yarn</hi> into Hair Shags, Tammies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believe there is now about <hi>London</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of twenty <hi>French</hi> for one <hi>Engliſh,</hi> either of Maſters or Workmen therein. I mention this, becauſe it is the great Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, of the multitudes of <hi>Engliſh</hi> who
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61473:20"/> want Bread, That proſecuting and driving away <hi>Foreigners,</hi> would give Relief to their Want; and ſo far hath it prevailed, that by inceſſant importunity they oblig'd the <hi>Company,</hi> for the better conſidering of the matter, to call a <hi>full Court;</hi> and further by their preſſing Intreaties had engaged a number of thoſe that were or had been their <hi>Work-maſters,</hi> to repreſent their caſe to the <hi>Court;</hi> and in order to their Relief, to requeſt, 1. That the <hi>Company</hi> would put their <hi>By-Laws</hi> in execution. 2. That they would give them leave to proſecute, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> thoſe that had not ſerved <hi>ſeven years</hi> an Apprentiſhip to the <hi>Trade.</hi> 3. That they would admit no more <hi>Foreigners</hi> to work on the <hi>Trade.</hi> To all which the <hi>Company</hi> gave all thoſe that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared full ſatisfaction, That they lay under an Obligation neither to do, nor to abet, or ſuffer any thing to be done contrary to the Agreement made with their Church; but that they would endeavour ſo to repreſent their caſe, that there might be Relief both for them and the Strangers alſo; but for acting thus, the <hi>Company</hi> is ſharply upbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and warmly reflected upon by the <hi>poor</hi> miſtaken Multitude: For tho' this hath been ſome ſmall cauſe of their Poverty by accident, as hath been before mentioned; yet cannot cure the Evil they labour under: But if I might, I would <hi>Adviſe</hi> or <hi>Perſwade</hi> (for it is unreaſonable in this caſe to talk of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61473:20"/> 
               <hi>Forcing</hi> or <hi>Prohibiting</hi>) People of all Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Age or Sex, to the wearing of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Ornaments of <hi>Silk</hi> or <hi>Grograin Yarn</hi> of <hi>Engliſh</hi> make; for this is the return of <hi>Engliſh Woollen Cloth,</hi> and nothing could conduce more to the advantage of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Merchants</hi> Trading to <hi>Turkey, Spain, Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and other <hi>European</hi> Parts, and is double advantage to <hi>England.</hi> The truth of which may be further demonſtrated in one ſmall but freſh inſtance, by which I believe more than one Merchant have been no ſmall Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers, I mean the great and ſudden diſuſe of <hi>Mohair Fringes,</hi> together with the decay of the <hi>Weaving and Button-making Trade,</hi> by which means ſome thouſand pounds worth of <hi>Mohair Yarn,</hi> which otherwiſe might have been ſold for ready Money at a Price, ſo ſunk and fell in its value, that it is ſince ſold for one third of what might then have been had for it; and I believe, that reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the decay by the Worm eating into it, and the loſs of Intereſt, even that third part was likewiſe conſumed (which had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe been laid out again in Cloth and Tin, and ſent to <hi>Turkey</hi>) as the Proprietor can tell by woful Experience: And I am ſure that our Womens great eſteem for <hi>Thread Fringes</hi> was a great occaſion thereof, and a great kindneſs to the <hi>Dutch.</hi> And therefore I intreat and beg of you, that you will uſe your utmoſt Intereſt and Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick to perſwade and prevail, that <hi>Camblet
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61473:21"/> Cloaks, Coats</hi> and <hi>Gowns, Silk Mohair,</hi> and <hi>Mohair Fringes and Buttons, and Manufactures here made of Silk and Grograin Yarn,</hi> may be the Wearing preferr'd and encourag'd: For this is the true Intereſt of the <hi>Turkey Trade,</hi> and in it the great Intereſt of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">(27.) From what hath been ſaid, I think it may plainly appear, That no leſs than a <hi>Prohibition</hi> or ſtop of the <hi>Home-Conſumption</hi> of all ſorts of <hi>Eaſt-India Silks and Stuffs,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>plain Perſian Taffaties,</hi> and ſuch-like of plain make, can preſerve the <hi>Silk-Weavers</hi> and <hi>Throſters</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and thoſe great Numbers that depend upon them, the good conſequence whereof hath been already ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrated: For if this be not grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thoſe Trades muſt utterly decay and ſink; for as matters now ſtand, by reaſon of the fore-mentioned Dangers, few Men that had an Eſtate would for the three years laſt paſt adventure it, the loſs being ſo certain; and as for ſuch as have and do trade upon Credit, they are forc'd to ſuch miſerable ſhifts as at laſt ends in extream Poverty: And the cauſe it ſelf, (I mean <hi>England</hi>'s Intereſt) is almoſt totally yielded up; deep deſpair, together with diſability, having ſo diſ-ſpirited and ſunk the Minds of the <hi>Engliſh Silk Manufacturers,</hi> that there is not <hi>Silk</hi> provided to ſupply the <hi>Mercers Shops,</hi> tho' they ſhould be willing to buy; all ſtand at gaze, and are only concern'd to ſee what the <hi>Parliament</hi> would do with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61473:21"/> them; they are falling into extream de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, in vain contriving to find out New Employments. And therefore I beg of, and beſeech you, good Sir, for GOD's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake, for your Countrey's ſake, and for the ſake of thoſe <hi>Numberleſs Multitudes of Poor</hi> before menrioned, that you would employ all your Intereſt to gain ſome <hi>effectual Prohibition</hi> of wearing any <hi>flower'd, ſpotted, or ſtrip'a Silk of Indian Make;</hi> and then I doubt not but ſuch a good Act, with example, would not only gain the preferrence at home, but alſo afford an opportunity, not only to our own <hi>Plantations,</hi> but alſo to many <hi>Neighbouring Countreys,</hi> to follow the Example; our <hi>Factors</hi> in moſt places commonly ſending their orders for ſuch Commodities as our ſelves moſt prefer and uſe. Nor let any think that ſuch a <hi>Prohibition</hi> would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable, if reſolved upon; for the firm Reſolution of an <hi>Engliſh Parliament</hi> is of force ſufficient to prevail in any good Cauſe which they ſhall heartily eſpouſe; as may be ſeen in the Buſineſs of <hi>Burying</hi> in <hi>Woollen,</hi> and the <hi>French Al-a-modes and Luſtrings,</hi> which I believe to be totally ſuppreſt: And I am confident the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves would not attempt the breach of ſuch a Law, if it were once obtain'd; and the <hi>Interlopers,</hi> or private Traders, might be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily prevented, and ſuch Rules propos'd, as might deter any other parts from impoſing them upon us, under the notion of their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61473:22"/> own Manufactures: But if the greateſt Evils muſt meet with no good Endeavours of Redreſs, we muſt be of all People moſt miſerable. Therefore, <hi>Dear Sir,</hi> endeavour that ſomething may be done by the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> before they Riſe, that may at leaſt give <hi>hopes,</hi> that their <hi>Cauſe</hi> ſhall in due time, be throughly <hi>Conſider'd:</hi> Such a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> or <hi>Vote</hi> wou'd give New <hi>Life</hi> to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as can ſtruggle out another ſeaſon, and <hi>hopes</hi> of good in time to the reſt; but the contrary, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tter Deſpair.</hi> For I think I may truly ſay, what looks like a Prophecy in one of their <hi>Papers</hi> about three years ſince, when contending for this <hi>Bill</hi> in <hi>Parliament, That if it were granted, is wou'd in a ſmall time ſo invigorate the Minds of all Fabrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors both in Silk, Wooll, and Grograin Yarn, that they would contend with all other Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, tho' Money ſhou'd continue as ſcarce as at preſent; and that the contrary wou'd diſcourage thoſe of greateſt Ability, to that degree, that the Out-Pariſhes of</hi> London, <hi>the Tower Hamb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and the Wool-Manufacturing Towns of</hi> England, <hi>would not be able to ſupport their Poor.</hi> And whether the Truth of this laſt part hath not been verified to purpoſe, I dare appeal to the <hi>Miniſters, Church-VVar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and Overſeers of the Poor:</hi> And I am ſure all the Inhabitants of thoſe Places muſt and will give a ſad Teſtimony both to the Truth of this, and what will be the only Remedy we can hope for, and that is, the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61473:22"/> 
               <hi>Prohibition</hi> requeſted: For had that Act then paſſed, it had ſaved the Lives of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who have ſince periſhed, and preſerved the Trade both of Weavers and Throſters above double the Number they now are.</p>
            <p n="28">(28.) And for your further Conviction, it may not be unſeaſonable here to add to the two fore-mentioned Acts concerning <hi>Button-making</hi> and <hi>Dying,</hi> a third inſtance of our former care, and that is, The Act to prevent <hi>Silk</hi> coming <hi>ready Thrown</hi> from <hi>India.</hi> For can any reaſonable Man living believe, that ſuch care ſhould be taken of <hi>Dyers</hi> and <hi>Throſters,</hi> and at the ſame time the <hi>VVeavers</hi> be wholly neglected, unleſs it be that the <hi>Dyers</hi> and <hi>Throſters,</hi> had and did make <hi>friends</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> but the <hi>VVeavers</hi> had <hi>none</hi> to inform in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half? Beſides, the Proviſion it ſelf, is ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual and ridiculous, if it be not reaſonable to grant this <hi>Prohibition;</hi> for no <hi>Silk</hi> is <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> but what is firſt <hi>thrown</hi> and <hi>dyed;</hi> and therefore ſo far as <hi>Silk-throwing</hi> and <hi>Dying,</hi> hath relation to <hi>VVeaving,</hi> thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> are inſignificant, and now both thoſe <hi>Trades</hi> are very ſenſible, that not only the <hi>VVell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being,</hi> but almoſt their <hi>Being,</hi> depends upon the Preſervation of the <hi>Silk-VVeaving,</hi> and that they ſhould have a very <hi>poor Trade,</hi> to be only employed in <hi>Throwing</hi> and <hi>Dying</hi> for <hi>Stitching</hi> and <hi>Sowing Silks,</hi> and ſome ſmall pittance for the <hi>Stockin-Frames,</hi> and the <hi>Button</hi> and <hi>Fringe-makers;</hi> and it is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61473:23"/> worrh obſervation, that the <hi>Eaſt-India Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies</hi> fingers itch'd, to gain this point alſo; for they did lately bring over a conſiderable quantity of <hi>Indian Thrown</hi> and <hi>Dyed Silk,</hi> which the <hi>Throſters</hi> and <hi>Dyers</hi> coming to the knowledge of, they beſtir'd themſelves, and made a <hi>Seizure</hi> thereof, but the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was patcht up I know not how; for the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> durſt not contend it, but are, or ſeem contented for the future, not to bring it over ſo <hi>Thrown or Dyed,</hi> but are reſolv'd to do us a <hi>further kindneſs,</hi> and ſave us the labour of the <hi>VVeaving,</hi> the <hi>prevention</hi> of which, is the only <hi>remedy</hi> we have to preſerve our ſelves and <hi>England</hi> from <hi>extream Poverty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">(29.) <hi>Sir,</hi> In behalf of thoſe great Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, concern'd in this Controverſie; I earneſtly Intreat you, to uſe your Intereſt with thoſe Gentlemen, who now have the management of the <hi>India Trade</hi> in their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that they wou'd be ſo kind to their <hi>poor Countrey-men,</hi> as to grant willingly what is here deſired; for it is not Reaſonable to think, that the Offer made by them to thoſe <hi>Weavers,</hi> who treated with them, will either be <hi>accepted</hi> by them, or <hi>allowed</hi> by the <hi>Parliament;</hi> which was to this effect, That if they wou'd ſo aſſiſt them, as to gain an Abatement of <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> upon <hi>Raw Silk, Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Yarn, and other unmanufactured Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> for Trade, they would be contented to load all <hi>Wrought Silks</hi> with <hi>Duties,</hi> to ſuch a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61473:23"/> degree, as might make it more profitable to bring the ſaid <hi>Raw Silks</hi> and other mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials to be Manufactured here, than to bring the <hi>Wrought Silks, Stuffs,</hi> or other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Manufactured Goods. But I ſhall offer you ſome Reaſons, why I think this Project will not take, or if it do, would be of no good uſe or Benefit.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe this would give a vaſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the <hi>Indian Trade,</hi> beyond that of the <hi>Turkey and Italian Merchant,</hi> and ſo would more and more obſtruct and deſtroy thoſe more Beneficial and Neceſſary Trades.</p>
            <p n="2">2. So Great a Duty, would be a ſtrong temptation to all Private <hi>Traders and Sail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> to venture their all in this <hi>Commodity,</hi> which is ſo <hi>Portable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It wou'd be no leſs temptation to other <hi>Nations,</hi> eſpecially our <hi>French and Dutch Friends,</hi> to impoſe them upon us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The forementioned reaſon of our Ladies humours, and unaccountable Fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Commodity, plainly ſhews, That nothing but an abſolute <hi>Prohibition</hi> of wearing thereof, can effectually prevent the Miſchief; for with them it is all in all, if it be <hi>Eaſt-India;</hi> be it never ſo <hi>dear,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo <hi>ugly,</hi> it then Pleaſeth, and no <hi>Price</hi> is too great for it.</p>
            <p n="30">(30.) Now this being plain matter of Fact, and evident Truth, What a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous condition are all our <hi>Engliſh Manufacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:61473:24"/> in, which are not already <hi>ſecured by Law,</hi> againſt this <hi>devouring Trade?</hi> As for the <hi>Throwſters</hi> and <hi>Dyers</hi> before mentioned, they are little Significant, if the <hi>Weavers</hi> be not Preſerved and Secured; but if, as the <hi>Eaſt-India Company</hi> pretends, they have a dear Bargain, and will have what they have bought, which they ſay, is no leſs, than a freedom to bring not only Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of Trade, and Productions of that Countreys Growth, but alſo whatſoever Manufactures they can make advantage by; then in few years they may, and doubtleſs will, Undo all before them, if not in the former inſtance of carrying <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Wooll</hi> to be there Manufactured, yet in projecting and making ſuch <hi>Cloth</hi> of <hi>Cotton Wooll,</hi> for Mens Garments, as ſhall as much outvye (or at leaſt be thought ſo) our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Cloth,</hi> as <hi>Indian Silks</hi> are thought by our vain Ladies to ſurpaſs <hi>Engliſh.</hi> The <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers</hi> they have already beat out of the Pit, little being left them to do, unleſs to mend and repair the breaches that happen to <hi>Indian Fans</hi> in their paſſage: I cannot ſay they have as yet carryed over any <hi>Stockin-Frames,</hi> but that they will not do it, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable; and then what will become of our ingenious <hi>Frame-knitting,</hi> and thoſe thouſands of poor People, that in ſeveral Counties of <hi>England,</hi> earn their bread by Knitting with Needles, when we ſhall have <hi>Eaſt-India Silk Stockins,</hi> far Cheaper, than
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61473:24"/> here they can be made of <hi>Wooll?</hi> But not to tire your Patience, Thus may the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pholſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> the <hi>Hatters,</hi> the <hi>Taylors,</hi> the <hi>Imbroide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> the <hi>Glovers,</hi> and others, too many to be named, be <hi>ſwallowed up</hi> by this <hi>All-De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Eaſt-India Trade,</hi> if they have this unlimited Power; for had they not the Materials themſelves Cheaper there, than here, (which yet they have by much) the very difference of charge in Workman-ſhip may deſtroy all before it, the Neceſſaries of Life, affording the <hi>Indians</hi> a better liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood for a <hi>penny,</hi> than the <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> for a <hi>ſhilling;</hi> and then by the Greatneſs of their Stock, bringing over whatever they deal with, in ſuch Vaſt Quantities, and by their Intereſt in Perſons of the beſt Rank and Quality, they can (by theſe and other like means) give the Preference to what they pleaſe; ſo that unleſs you can believe them to be <hi>ſtrange Self-denying Men,</hi> they may at their pleaſure, Ruin, in a manner, all the <hi>Trades and Manufactories of England.</hi> I have lately received Information of one inſtance of this Nature, which mightily concerns us, which is, That ſeveral <hi>Molds and Tools,</hi> for making <hi>Pewter,</hi> have been lately made, and carryed down in <hi>Coaches,</hi> near to <hi>Thames-ſtreet,</hi> ſuppoſed to be for the uſe of the <hi>Spaniards and Portugueſe;</hi> they having obtain'd our <hi>Tin,</hi> on Terms likely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy our Manufacturing of <hi>Pewter:</hi> but I doubt and fear, That they are rather pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61473:25"/> for the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> where there is plenty of <hi>Tin;</hi> and then we may bid fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to the <hi>Pewterers Trade;</hi> and if it ſhou'd be ſo, our <hi>Cornwal Tin-Mines,</hi> will alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Mortal Wound: This matter is worth a full diſcovery, which by all the enquiry I have made, I could not yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to, but for ſo much as I relate, I am well aſſured, though all the Mold-Makers deny the thing, which makes me the more ſuſpitious, that they are going the ſame way, which the <hi>Engliſh Weavers, Patterns, and Pattern-drawers,</hi> formerly went; but whereſoever they go, I fear it will be much to the Prejudice of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="31">(31.) But I am not willing to be miſtak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en as an enemy, either to the <hi>Eaſt-India Trade</hi> or <hi>Company;</hi> I heartily wiſh a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reconciliation of all Parties, and them a Trade as Large and Proſperous as their own hearts can deſire, could it be conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent with the Publick Welfare of <hi>England,</hi> which if the loſs of the Silk Manufacture would advance, I ſhould gladly ſee it Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crific'd to ſo good an end: But I am ſure, and Truth it ſelf compells me to declare, That the greater the <hi>Eaſt-India Trade</hi> is in general, the greater Prejudice it is to <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> But ſince the errour hath ſpread like a general Infection, and every Kingdom and Nation, that can, ſtriveth to outvie each other in this bewitching Trade; may the <hi>Engliſh</hi> exceed all, and be Proſperous;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61473:25"/> and it is, and always was my opinion, That an Incorporation, or Company, Wiſely and Honeſtly Manag'd, is the beſt way to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it on, and prevent being Inſulted or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon by the <hi>Great Mogul,</hi> or his, or any others <hi>Subjects;</hi> but then here lies the great danger, That ſuch a <hi>Body</hi> can <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> or <hi>Requeſt,</hi> or <hi>Oblige,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Purſe</hi> can <hi>Fee</hi> and <hi>Bribe</hi> at that extravagant Rate, as to make <hi>Friends</hi> amongſt <hi>Inconſiderate or Covetous Men,</hi> to the carrying on any <hi>Cauſe</hi> or <hi>Intereſt</hi> they purſue, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> never ſo <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive</hi> to the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> unleſs the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative Power</hi> pleaſe to <hi>interpoſe</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</hi> it: Nor have I the leaſt intent to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect, either on particular Perſons, or Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages; I have as much Reſpect for, and great an eſteem of moſt of thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons concern'd in that Trade, as any man whatſoever; and I do verily believe, that many of them, would never contend in this matter, had they throughly and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally weigh'd and conſider'd the Evil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences thereof; but the greater part, is either actually govern'd by the leſs, or elſe ſubtilly manag'd and govern'd by a few, whoſe Intereſt, Power or Parts, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tops the reſt; and if theſe judge, that hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paid their Money, they may make the beſt Advantage of their Bargain, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue their Deſigns, whoever Suffers, the reſt follow their Leaders, without further Conſideration: But with their good leave,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61473:26"/> I think Eight <hi>per Cent,</hi> and as great Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as can be given, or deſired, to be better than any Trade, and I hope will not entitle any Perſons to a further Right of Undoing others, and the Ruin of our Home Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures. But our <hi>Wiſe Legiſlators,</hi> muſt and will be <hi>Judges</hi> in this Caſe, and to them I refer it. And 'tis worth their moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Conſideration, That when we have brought the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to be as much in love (as our ſelves) and to uſe theſe <hi>Indian Silks</hi> and <hi>Stuffs,</hi> for whoſe Clymate they are more fitting than for ours, they may not come under the Government of a Prince, who will quickly teach them Navigation enough, to exchange their Weſtern Cargo's of <hi>Bullion,</hi> for theſe <hi>Eaſtern Silks and Stuffs,</hi> without our help, which will likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, at leaſt, a Moyety of our <hi>Woollen Manufacture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="32">(32.) And with ſubmiſſion, I do think this further matter may not be unworthy the Conſideration of that <hi>Auguſt Aſſembly,</hi> That whilſt the <hi>French</hi> ſend their <hi>Ships</hi> to <hi>India,</hi> both for <hi>Materials, Productions,</hi> and <hi>Manufactures</hi> of that Country, they care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Support and Increaſe their <hi>Home Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacturers,</hi> and now buy up Silk (beyond what they ever did) and <hi>Grograin Yarn</hi> (which formerly they did not) in <hi>Turkey,</hi> whilſt our <hi>Turky-Merchants Factors</hi> only look on; becauſe the <hi>Manufacturers</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> being Ruin'd by this <hi>Indian Torrent,</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:61473:26"/> nothing will ſell here at the Price they muſt give there: And thus the <hi>French</hi> ſecures his <hi>Intereſt</hi> at <hi>Home,</hi> and likewiſe comes in for a <hi>large ſhare</hi> in the <hi>deſolation</hi> of thoſe <hi>Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facturing Countreys,</hi> that undo themſelves, or will be thus Deſtroy'd: And who can blame the <hi>Turky Merchants</hi> for deſiſting their Trade? For our <hi>VVeavers</hi> and <hi>Silk Throwſters</hi> cannot, as matters are; and for that Reaſon have not provided to ſupply the wants of the <hi>Mercers,</hi> the two laſt years, which if they had or did, yet the <hi>Turkey Merchants</hi> have not <hi>Silk</hi> to carry on the <hi>Trade,</hi> and for this reaſon muſt deſiſt to buy <hi>Cloth;</hi> and thus the deſtruction of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s <hi>Trade</hi> approacheth; and that the fall of Lands in value will ſoon follow, is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; the late advance of which, proceeds more from the Judgment of GOD upon theſe parts of the World, than any other cauſe: For now both <hi>Corn,</hi> and <hi>Wooll,</hi> and all other like Neceſſaries, advance not in their value by the <hi>goodneſs of Trade,</hi> but by the <hi>ill Crops, and ſcarcity thereof,</hi> (chiefly in other Countreys) which muſt be again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed by the advancing the Price of the <hi>Productions of other Countreys,</hi> (as we do in <hi>Claret,</hi> as well as <hi>Silk</hi>) and if we cannot do the one as well as the other, we loſe our <hi>Trade:</hi> And matters may be as well mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for the ſupport of our Manufactures, as they are by others for their own in other parts: And we may then give as good a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61473:27"/> Price in <hi>Turkey</hi> as the <hi>French,</hi> and alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the <hi>Dutch</hi> from buying up here thoſe Neceſſaries of <hi>Silk, Grograin,</hi> and <hi>Cotton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arn,</hi> for which our <hi>Turkey Merchants</hi> now can find little other good Markets.</p>
            <p n="33">(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3.) Having confined my ſelf chiefly to the particular Intereſt of the Weaving <hi>Manufactory,</hi> I have avoided thoſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that are or may be brought to prove the prejudice the <hi>Eaſt-India Trade</hi> is, to the <hi>General Trade of the Kingdom,</hi> as well in the <hi>Materials</hi> for <hi>Trade,</hi> as in the <hi>Manufactured Silks,</hi> which I truly think it is. But thoſe Arguments have been already handled by much better Pens in ſeveral Printed Tracts, and eſpecially in a late Piece by that indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble Champion for <hi>Norwich,</hi> Mr. <hi>Loam,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his late <hi>Anſwer to the moſt conſiderable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ections</hi> that are brought in defence of the ſaid Trade; as alſo in his <hi>Caſe of the Engliſh Manufact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Trading in VVooll,</hi> preſented to the Parliament; and for this Reaſon both the <hi>Turkey,</hi> and other <hi>Merchants,</hi> may judg this my diſcourſe to be of little concern to them, <hi>Raw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cotton Yarn and Wooll,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udicing their <hi>Trade</hi> as well as if <hi>ready Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactured,</hi> but to me the Remedy of that ſeems unpracticable, unleſs all <hi>Europe</hi> would agree to damn the Eaſt India Trade it ſelf, as to that particular; and we had better be ſubject to one evil, than to that and a greater; ſuch as I take the <hi>diſpeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling</hi> our <hi>Countrey,</hi> by <hi>Deſtroying</hi> our <hi>Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:61473:27"/> to be: And cou'd theſe <hi>Materials,</hi> be the return of our own <hi>Productions</hi> (as it is by the <hi>Turky Merchants</hi>) and not of <hi>Bulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (as it is by the <hi>Eaſt-India Merchant</hi>) I think it might be much at one, to the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Intereſt,</hi> whether they had them from <hi>India</hi> or <hi>Turkey;</hi> yea, and as it is, we might the better bear it, if theſe Commodities were again <hi>exported</hi> with ſuch advantage as they ſometimes pretend, but without proof: For when they have been preſſed with that dangerous Argument of ſending away our Money to the <hi>Indies,</hi> they inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on this in their Defence, That nine parts in ten of their <hi>Wrought Silks imported,</hi> were again <hi>exported;</hi> but when in the laſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie they defeated that <hi>good Bill</hi> in the <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> then finding the Nation was bewitch'd to the uſe of their <hi>Silks,</hi> and to a belief of the Neceſſity and Benefit of their Trade, but chiefly depending on the Friends they had made, then they changed thir Note, and loudly proclaimed that the <hi>Eaſt-India Trade</hi> would be nothing worth, if they might not be allowed to uſe them in <hi>England;</hi> for that (as they then truly ſaid) <hi>Nine parts in Ten, were conſumed here.</hi> I hope all theſe Reaſons will prevail for the Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition deſired.</p>
            <p n="34">(34.) As to what is commonly objected of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Practice herein, and Profit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, it hath formerly been truly and wiſely obſerved, That <hi>one Pariſh in</hi> London <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61473:28"/> more Eaſt-India Silks than all the Seven Provinces of</hi> Holland: And ſuch an Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Practice, had ſaved me this labour; as to the largeneſs of their <hi>Eaſt-India Trade,</hi> I know they have had a great ſhare in the Ruine of <hi>Europe,</hi> for the enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves; but in this particular of <hi>wrought Silks,</hi> we have <hi>greatly out-done them.</hi> For 'tis obſerved, that one <hi>Engliſh Ship</hi> hath at once brought more of that pernicious Commodity, than all the <hi>Dutch Fleets</hi> the year round, and that for conſiderable time paſt. But if we wou'd do well, we muſt with the promoting our <hi>Navigation</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe conſider that we have a large Tract of <hi>fruitful Land, rich Mines, profitable Sheep and Cattel,</hi> and theſe we muſt likewiſe improve to the <hi>inriching</hi> our Countrey with People, and ſo as they may live by their Labour.</p>
            <p n="35">(35.) Sir, I fear I have quite tir'd your Patience, upon which I will not treſpaſs much longer, and therefore now drawing to a Concluſion, I ſolemnly proteſt, that to the beſt of my Judgment and Knowledge, I have herein declared or writ nothing for any other motive, end or reaſon, than the <hi>Good</hi> of my <hi>Country in general,</hi> and which I am ſure the Support and Welfare of thoſe poor Manufacturers, for whom I am a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate tho' mean Advocate, tends to: And I cannot omit to tell you, That ſome laugh at, and ridicule the Notion of Peoples <hi>periſhing</hi> and <hi>ſtarving,</hi> which I before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61473:28"/> And indeed, ſome years ſince, who would have imagined that ſuch a thing could be, in ſuch a plentiful Countrey as <hi>England?</hi> But alas! I am now daily an <hi>eye</hi> or <hi>ear Witneſs</hi> of the contrary. And if that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who receives a <hi>bruiſe</hi> or <hi>ſtab,</hi> and for ſome time after <hi>lives</hi> and <hi>lingers,</hi> and <hi>at laſt dies</hi> thereof, is as certainly <hi>murthered,</hi> as he that is <hi>ſtabb'd to the Heart,</hi> or <hi>his Brains beat out;</hi> I am certain that for ſome years paſt, many have <hi>periſhed</hi> for want of neceſſary <hi>Food, Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Lodging</hi> and <hi>Fire,</hi> according to the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity of our Climate, and ſo <hi>periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and dying by degrees,</hi> I cannot but judge them as truly <hi>ſtarved,</hi> as if they had been kept from <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Rayment altogether;</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perhaps they may be ſaid to periſh more <hi>miſerably,</hi> becauſe more <hi>ſlowly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="36">(36.) If I am herein guilty of any Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, 'tis of my <hi>Judgment,</hi> not my <hi>Will;</hi> and I ſhall readily ſubmit to any Conviction I ſhall be made ſenſible of; and I do expect to be ſharply attack'd by ſuch as my Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation renders me uncapable to contend with: But I have ſo great Satisfaction in the Goodneſs, Juſtice and Reaſonableneſs of this Cauſe, that I fear nothing; and doubt not but the Righteouſneſs thereof will raiſe me up Seconds that will better maintain the Reaſonableneſs of what is here deſir'd, for that <hi>vaſt</hi> and <hi>Neceſſary Body</hi> of <hi>Engliſh Silk-Weavers, Throſters, and their Dependents,</hi> viz. As firm a <hi>Probi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ition</hi> againſt the <hi>Home-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:61473:29"/> of <hi>figur'd, flower'd, ſtitch'd,</hi> and <hi>ſtrip'd Silks,</hi> as <hi>Wit</hi> can invent, or <hi>Law</hi> make; and then to expend their <hi>plain</hi> among us, is more, or at leaſt as much, as they ought to deſire, if they value the <hi>Publick Good</hi> more than their <hi>Private Intereſt.</hi> And by this means would Employment be provided for <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded Souldiers,</hi> of whom great numbers belong to the <hi>Weaving Trade,</hi> and its <hi>Dependants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="37">(37.) And for Concluſion and Confirmation of all I have ſaid, I refer you to that great Maſter of <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Merchandize,</hi> Sir <hi>Joſiah Child,</hi> who by his late little acting in the <hi>Eaſt-India-Company,</hi> ſeems to adhere to this his former Principle, (however it is ſaid his Practice ſometime greatly contradicted it) and with which the <hi>Weavers</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded their former Paper to the <hi>Lords,</hi> when laſt defeated: And thus ſaith he, <hi>Whatſoever advances the value of Land in Purchaſe, improves the Rent of Farms, increaſeth the Bulk of Foreign Trade, multiplies Domeſtick Artificers, inclineth the Nation to Thriftineſs, employs the Poor, or increaſeth the Stock of the People, muſt be procuring Cauſes of Riches: But a Foreign Expence, eſpecially of Foreign Manufactures, is the worſt Expence a Nation can be inclinable to, and ought to be prevented,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In fine, Sir, 'Tis believ'd the Liberty given the Preſs was, That you might conſtantly receive full and free Information in all things relating to Publick Affairs, and the Good of the Kingdom; and that, to the beſt of my <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> I have given in this Caſe; and I bleſs GOD I have not writ this for Bread, or any other Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, but as before ſaid: And I thought that the making it more Publick than for your ſingle Satisfaction, may not be Unacceptable or Uſeleſs. And whatſoever your Wiſdom determies herein, or whatever my own Sentiments, or Belief, is thereof, I ſhall Acquieſce with all Due Submiſſion, for I am, Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to Command, A. N.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61473:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
